A Guide to the Preston Family (Alice Preston Moore Collection) Papers, 1749-1882, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Preston Family (Alice Preston Moore Collection) Papers, 1749-1882, n.d
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1962-004
1.5 cu. ft. 4 boxes; 1 oversize
The collection consists of family papers, receipts, correspondence, and original and photocopied materials relating to the Preston family, primarily William and Susanna Smith Preston, John Preston, and William Ballard Preston, dating from the 1740s to the 1880s. Other materials include 19th and 20th century genealogy research on the Prestons.
Patton, James, Preston family, Montgomery County, Va.; Preston family, Montgomery County, Va.; Preston, John, 1764-1827; Preston, Susanna Smith, 1740-1823; Preston, William Ballard, 1805-1862; Preston, William, 1729-1783
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Preston Family (Alice Preston Moore Collection) Papers were deposited with the University Libraries in the 1960s. There were later transferred to Special Collections.
Biographical Information
William and Susanna Smith Preston
Smithfield Plantation is the historic home of the Preston family, one of the founding families of Blacksburg and Montgomery County, Virginia. It was built by William Preston (1729-1783), who emigrated from northern Ireland with his family in 1737. He married Susanna Smith in 1761 and settled at Greenfield in Botetourt County in 1769. Preston established himself as a leader in the Virginia frontier by serving in the militia in the French and Indian and Revolutionary wars, in the House of Burgesses representing Augusta County from 1766 to 1768 and Botetourt County in 1769, and as County Lieutenant of Fincastle and Montgomery. He was appointed surveyor of Fincastle County in 1772 and moved his family to that area. He built Smithfield, named in honor of his wife, in 1773. Smithfield was the birthplace and home of three Virginia governors, including James Patton Preston (son of William), and John Buchanan Floyd and John Floyd, Jr. (grandsons of William).
John Preston
John Preston, eldest son of William and Susanna (Smith) Preston, was born in 1764 at "Greenfield" in Botetourt County, Virginia. He periodically served in the Virginia militia throughout his lifetime. Preston was elected a member of the Virginia House of Delegates, representing Botetourt County in 1783, as well as Montgomery County in 1791 and again in 1803-1804. He served as a member of the Virginia Senate from 1792- 1799.
In 1792, Preston was named as a trustee in the act that established Christiansburg, Virginia in 1792, and served as a clerk of its first Board of Trustees. In 1798 he served as a trustee in the act that established Blacksburg, Virginia. In 1795, Preston became a Lieutenant Colonel, commanding the Third Regiment of Artillery. In 1799, he was elected Brigadier General, and given command of the brigade for Wythe, Montgomery, and Monroe Counties.
Later in 1810, Preston was appointed by the Virginia General Assembly to be the Treasurer of Virginia, serving until 1819. An audit of the treasurer's books found that Preston's accounts were in arrears, and a judgement was issued against Preston for 87 thousand dollars. To meet the obligation, Preston transferred a number of properties to trustees, who were to oversee their sale and the payment of funds into the treasury.
Preston married Mary Radford in 1798, and after her death in 1810, married Eliza Ann Carrington Mayo in 1811. He had seven children with his first wife and one with his second. When not on active military duty, Preston resided at "Smithfield" with his mother until his marriage, after which he lived at "Horseshoe". He died at Greenfield in 1827.
Scope and Content
The collection include business transactions, land surveys, and general store accounts (1745-1789) relating to William and Susannah Smith Preston; correspondence, business transactions, and notes on farm affairs (1782-1828) relating to their son, John Preston; correspondence and land surveys (1840-1882) relating to John, William A., and Alfred G. Preston; correspondence (1848-1861) relating to William Ballard Preston; and a day book (1789-1820) of the Prestons of Washington County.
Arrangement
The majority of the collection is arranged in series by family member/branch of the family: William and Susanna Smith Preston, William Ballard Preston, John and Elizabeth Preston, John Preston, and James Patton. Two additional series include materials from individuals in later generations and branches of the Preston family and genealogical/historical research. Within each of these series, materials are in chronological order.
Index Terms
Persons:
Patton, James, Preston family, Montgomery County, Va.; Preston, John, 1764-1827; Preston, Susanna Smith, 1740-1823; Preston, William Ballard, 1805-1862; Preston, William, 1729-1783
Family Names:
Preston family, Montgomery County, Va.
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.)
Contents List
- William (1729-1783) and Susanna Smith (1740-1823) Preston Papers, 1783, 1817, n.d
  - William Preston Land Inventory (at the time of his death), June 1783 (Folder 1)
  - Susanna Preston Will, December 1817 (Folder 1)
  - William and Susannah Preston-Land Surveys (Box-folder 4-2)
  - William and Susannah Preston-General Store Accounts (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Receipts, Bills, Promises to Pay (Box-folder 4-4)
  - William Preston Materials-Photocopies (Box-folder 4-5)
- William Ballard Preston (1805-1862) Papers, 1852, n.d
  - William Ballard Preston-Speech, c. 1852 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - William Ballard Preston-Letters, Speeches, Newspaper Articles-Photostatic Copies (Box-folder 2-2)
  - William Ballard Preston-Shackleford's Note Cards (Box-folder 2-3)
- John (1700-1747) and Elizabeth (1700-1776) Preston Papers, 1749-1772
  - John and Elizabeth Preston Papers, 1749-1772 (Box-folder 4-1)
- John Preston (1764-1827) Papers, 1782-1828, n.d
  - John Preston Papers (Son of William and Susanna), 1782-1828 (Box-folder 4-6)
  - John Preston Papers, 1789-1793 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - John Preston-Copies of Letters, 1799-1800 (Box-folder 4-8)
  - John Preston Papers (Box-folder 4-7)
- James Patton Papers, 1750
  - James Patton-Thomas Hughston Indenture, November 1750 (Folder 1)
- Papers from Other Preston Family Members, 1779-1882, n.d
  - Robert and Margaret Rhea Preston-Receipts, Surveys, Letters, 1779-1832 (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Preston Day Book, Washington County, Virginia, 1782-1820 (Box-folder 3-4)
  - McDowell/Prestons-Photocopies of Letters, 1824-1825 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - John Preston, William A. Preston, Alfred G. Preston Papers, 1840-1882 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Photocopies of Papers Relating to William, John, and Francis S. Preston (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Records dealing with Family of William Madison Peyton- Accessioned June 3, 1982; Records dealing with Descendants of Elizabeth Preston Madison, Eldest Child of William and Susannah Smith Preston (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Unidentified Original Papers (Box-folder 4-10)
  - Fragments from two letters, one possibly by Letitia Preston Breckinridge or Letitia Preston Floyd; the other author is unknown (Folder 1)
- Genealogy and Newspaper Clippings
  - Typescript copy of William Bowker Preston's "Preston Genealogy" (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Typescript Genealogical Notes, Historical Memoirs, of the Preston Family (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Newspaper Clippings on Preston Family Members (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Speech, Notes, etc. on Preston Family Homes, Smithfield and Greenfield (Box-folder 1-4)